Guide to the Frank Clyde Brown papers, 1912-1974 RL.00160
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Personal Papers, 1912-1974; 1
  - Collected Articles and Papers Subseries, 4
    - Paul Bunyon and Other Great Heroes. Douglas Saekman. 13 pp. (Box 27)
    - Pennsylvania German Folk-Medicine in Waterloo Co., Ontaria. Journal of American Folklore. July-Sept. 1936. J. Frederick Doering. 5 pp. (Box 27)
    - Photographs Connected with F. C. Brown Collection., 10 photographs (Box 27)
    - Place Names in North Carolina, 1939. Prof. George P. Wilson. 19 pp. (Box 28)
    - Plantation Memories. Fanny C. Waters. (n.d.) (Box 28)
    - Plea for Sympathetic Interest in Folklore. Paper before N. C. Folklore Society. Haywood Parker. 9 pp. (Box 28)
    - Popular Ballads Recorded in Knoxville, Tennessee. Southern Folklore Quarterly Vol. II, No. 2, 1938. 15 pp. (Box 28)
    - Popular Etymology. South Atlantic Quarterly, Jan. 1914. Reed Smith. 10 pp. (Box 28)
    - Present-Day Ballad, A. Origin of one ballad. Prof. T. P. Harrison. 6 pp. (Box 28)
    - Primitive Taboos Against Woman, Jan. 17, 1935. Rubye Fogel. 22 pp. (Box 28)
    - Proceedings of First Annual Meeting N. C. Folklore Society, Raleigh, March 24, 1913. 6 pp. (Box 28)
    - Program of N. C. Folklore Society, 1927. (Box 28)
    - Proverbs and Allusions in Twelfth Night. Philologic Quarterly, Vol. VI, No. 3. M. P. Tilley. 5 pp. (Box 28)
    - Provisional Checklist of Disks in Archives of American Folk Song, 1937. John A. Lomax, Curator. 39 pp. (Box 28)
    - Pulling Chanteys. Collected and Arranged by Cecil Sharp. London: Novello and Co. Novello's School Songs. 19 pp. (Box 28)
    - Racial Feeling in Negro Poetry. South Atlantic Quarterly, Jan. 1922. Newman I. White. 16 pp. (Box 28)
    - Racial Traits in the Negro Song. Sewanee Review, July 1920. Newman I. White. 9 pp. (Box 28)
    - Religion of Primitive Man, Jan. 21, 1936. William Dalzell Trader. 17 pp. (Box 28)
    - Return of the Dead in Ballad Literature. Edward Cox. Reprint from the Sewanee Review, July, 1912. (Box 28)
    - Roumanian Folk Tales Retold from the Original. University of Maine Studies, June 1925. Jacob Bernard Segall. 106 pp. (Box 28)
    - Sea Superstitions, Nov. 28, 1932. Ann Ingles. 21 pp. (Box 28)
    - Selection of Collected Folk Songs. Ed. Cecil J. Sharp and R. Vaughan Williams, 1909. London: Novello & Co. 43 pp. (Box 28)
    - Shakespeare and North Carolina Folklore, Dec. 6, 1940. Prof. George P. Wilson. 22 pp. (Box 28)
    - Similes from the Folk Speech of the South. Southern Folklore Quarterly, Dec. 1940. Included in Brown Collection. J. D. Clark. 22 pp., 2 copies (Box 28)
    - Singing South, The: Folksong in Recent Fiction. Sewanee Review, July 1936. Arthur Palmer Hudson. 27 pp. (Box 28)
    - Sixth National Folk Festival. Washington Post, April 27, 1929. 8 pp. (Box 28)
    - Soldier's Suit of Grey, C. B. Sinclair and C. C. Ilsley. Sheet music. Published by Blackmar & Bro., Augusta, Georgia, 1864. (Box 28)
    - Some Ballads of North Carolina. N. C. Booklet, July, 1911. John A. Lomax. 17 pp. (Box 28)
    - Some Curious Negro Names. Southern Folklore Quarterly, Dec. 1939. Arthur Palmer Hudson. 14 pp. (Box 28)
    - Some Folk Words. American Speech, Feb. 1930. Thomas P. Harrison. 5 pp., includes mss (Box 28)
    - Some Legends of Eastern North Carolina. Read at N. C. Folklore Society meeting Dec. 3, 1926. Dr. Richard Dillard. 19 pp. (Box 28)
    - Some Songs Traditional in the United States. Journal of American Folklore. April-June, 1916. Albert H. Tolman. 43 pp. (Box 28)
    - Some Southern Folk Remedies, and Earlier Parallels, 1936. Prof. George P. Wilson. 20 pp. (Box 28)
    - Some Western Ontario Folk Beliefs and Practices. Journal of American Folklore. Jan-March, 1938. J. Frederick and Eileen E. Doering. 9 pp. (Box 29)
    - Song Ballads, etc. Known in Missouri--Partial List. Missouri Folklore Society. 7 pp. (Box 29)
    - Songs and Rhymes from the South. Jounral of American Folklore. April-June, 1915. E. C. Perrow. 60 pp. (Box 29)
    - Songs and Singers--notes. Mrs. M. M. Sutton. 5 pp. (Box 29)
    - Songs Known by P. D. Midgett's Uncle, Wanchese, Roanoke Island. List of 78, 1920. P. D. Midgett, Jr. (Box 29)
    - South Carolina Folk Tales. Animals and Supernatural Beings. Bulletin of University of South Carolina, 1941. W. P. A. Writer's Program, Mabel Montgomery, State Supervisor. 124 pp. (Box 29)
    - Southern Folklore Quarterly for March & June 1937, Sept. & Dec. 1938, March, June, & Dec. 1939, March & June 1940, June 1943., 3 folders; 10 issues (Box 29)
    - Southern Highland Versions of Over-Sea Ballads. Paper before N. C. Folklore Society. Mrs. J. C. Campbell. 17 pp. (Box 29)
    - Southern Parallels to Newell's Games and Songs. Mary Belle Kearney. 15 pp. (Box 29)
    - Southron's Watch-Word!, The. M. F. Bigney and Stephen Glover. Sheet music. Published by Blackmar & Bro., Augusta, Georgia, 1861. (Box 29)
    - Spell of the Moon, The. Robert Baker Wynne. (n.d.) (Box 29)
    - Study of Folklore in Webster's Duchess of Malfi and Its Relations to Other Elizabethan Drama. Jan., 1934. LaVerne Roasch. 36 pp. (Box 29)
    - Study of Proverbs, The. B. J. Whiting, et. Al. Reprint from Modern Language Forum, Vol. 24, No. 2, June 1939. (Box 29)
    - Suffolk Miracle, The. They Brough Along Their Songs, IV, in Southern Literary Messenger, 1940. Frank L. Baer. 8 pp. (Box 29)
    - Sun Worship. Elizabeth Powell. 26 pp. (Box 29)
    - Superstitions About Jewels and Gems, 1942. Jane S. Cole. 18 pp. (Box 29)
    - Superstition And Supernaturalism in Connection with Lord Byron. George Harwell. 33 pp. (Box 29)
    - Superstitions of the Horseshoe, 1936. Mary Ann Cates. 9 pp. (Box 29)
    - Swastika, The: A Link Between the Old World and the New? Kitchener, Ontario, 1927. John F. Doering. 4 pp. (Box 29)
    - Syllabus of Kentucky Folk Songs. Transylvania University Studies, Lexington, Kentucky, 1911. Hubert G. Shearing and Josiah H. Combs. 43 pp. (Box 29)
    - Themes Common to English and German Balladry. Modern Language Quarterly, March 1940. Archer Taylor. 13 pp. (Box 30)
    - Thirty and One Folk Songs From the Southern Mountains. Carl Fischer, Inc., Boston, 1929. With music. Bascom Lamar Lunsford and Lamar Stringfield. 56 pp. (Box 30)
    - Three Ravens, The. Susan Sheppard. 21 pp. (Box 30)
    - Three Ravens, The, 1934. C. E. Phillips, Jr. 20 pp. (Box 30)
    - Three Ravens, The. Bernard R. Shelley. 37 pp. (Box 30)
    - Three Ravens, The, 1935. Kelvin Ray. 15 pp. (Box 30)
    - Three Ravens, The, 1942. Helen Schmidt. 26 pp. (Box 30)
    - Totemism, 1936. Elizabeth Sutton. 19 pp. (Box 30)
    - Tradition, and Folk Singing. Two notes. Mrs. M. M. Sutton. (Box 30)
    - Traditions and Legends of the Jews. W. H. Ripley, 7 pp. (Box 30)
    - Traditional Ballad in America, 1933. P. M. L. A. Jan-March, 1934. Reed Smith. 12 pp. (Box 30)
    - Traditional Ballad in the South, The. Journal of American Folklore. Jan-March, 1914. Reed Smith. 12 pp. (Box 30)
    - Traditional Songs from Galway & Mayo. Collected and edited by Mrs. Costello. Irish Folk Song Society, 1918. 149 pp. (Box 30)
    - Tragic Art of Balladry, The. South Atlanatic Quarterly. July 1915. Edward Godfrey Cox. 17 pp. (Box 30)
    - Twa Sisters, The. Thomas Johnson. 36 pp. (Box 30)
    - Twa Sister, The, 1935. Margaret H. Humbert. 86 pp. (Box 30)
    - Twa Sisters, The, 1940. Annabel Snow. 62 pp. (Box 30)
    - Types of the Folk Tale, the Folklore Fellows Communication, Helsinki, 1928. Anti Aarne (translated and enlarged by Stith Thompson). 276 pp. (Box 30)
    - Vampire, The, 1943. Green Smitheal, Jr. 15 pp. (Box 30)
    - Vampires. C. W. Reeves. 9 pp. (Box 30)
    - Vassals Family and the Cape Fear in the 17th Century, The: Address to N. C. Folklore Society, Dec. 1921. James Sprunt. 22 pp. (Box 30)
    - Virginia Folk-Sayings, from Word Book of Va. Speech (list). B. W. Green. 26 pp., 2 copies (Box 30)
    - Virginia Folklore Society Circular. Department of Public Instruction. Richmond, Virginia, 1914. 12 pp. (Box 30)
    - Voodoo Fire in Haiti. Literary Guild of America, New York. 1935. Richard A. Loederer. 274 pp. (Box 31)
    - Voodoo Origins and Practices, Survey of, 1943. Edward Dreyer. 18 pp. (Box 31)
    - Voodooism. Edward Dreyer. 13 pp. (Box 31)
    - Werewolves, 1935. Margaret Humbert. 31 pp. (Box 31)
    - White Man in the Woodpile, The: Some Influences on Negro Secular Songs. American Speech, Feb. 1923. Newman I. White. 9 pp. (Box 31)
    - Wife of Usher's Well, The, 1936. Lucille Pierce. 51 pp. (Box 31)
    - Wife of Usher's Well, The, 1942. Eloise Davis. 46 pp. (Box 31)
    - Wife of Usher's Well, 1942. Loraine Benz. 51 pp. (Box 31)
    - Witchcraft in Old Salem, 1941. W. T. Sadler, Jr. 23 pp. (Box 31)
    - Word- Lists From the South, Publications of the American Dialect Society, No. 2, Nov. 1944. (Box 31)
  - Index Subseries, 5
    - Chronological Index of Personal Correspondence, 1912-1934 (Box 33)
    - Chronological Index of Personal Correspondence, 1935-1943 (Box 34)
    - Index of Articles from Journal of American Folklore (Box 32)
    - Index of Folklore Studies (Box 32)
    - Index of Personal Correspondence re: folklore (Box 32)
    - Master Bibliography of Folklore Works (Box 32)
- General Editors' Papers, 43 boxes
  Drafts of publication include the table of contents, title page, and other materials, for Volume 1 and of the general introduction, as well as other miscellaneous materials. Successive progress reports on the project include the Classification Scheme, where White sets out an extended version of Brown's sixteen-point system of folklore classification by which White organized the folklore contributions. Divisions set out included: husbandry, omens, tokens, luck-signs, folk-medicine, magic, divination, housewifery, folk-sermons, pseudoscience, words, place-names, riddles and sayings, children's sayings, games, customs, legends, ballads, and songs. The series also includes newspaper and magazine reviews, correspondence, financial papers, and administrative materials.
  Finally, the series includes a vast collection of folklore typescripts, both original and carbon copies, of each item in the collection, arranged according to the Classification Scheme. These were prepared by White. There are numerous references to African American customs as well as folklore traditions in Europe carried over to the United States.
  - Drafts for publication of table of contents, title page, etc., for Volume 1 and of the general introduction (Box 35)
  - Successive reports on the progress of the publication project (Box 35)
  - Newspaper and magazine reviews of project (Box 35)
  - Correspondence and financial papers concerning the publication project, undated (Box 35)
  - Correspondence among the editors, undated (Box 36-37)
  - Indexes to the typescripts, undated; 2
    - Catalog of contributors, undated; 17 folders (Box 38)
    - Guide to Husbandry, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Omens, Luck-Signs, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Folk Medicine, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Magic, Charms, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Divination, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Housewifery, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Folk-Sermons, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Pseudoscience, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Folk-Expressions, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Origins of Place Names, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Riddles, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Proverbs, Similes, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Child Rhymes, Sayings, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Traditional Games, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Customs, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Legends, Folk-Tales, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
    - Guide to Folk Songs, undated; 1 folders (Box 39)
  - Transcripts, Original A, undated; 3
    - 1:A-1:K and unclassified. Husbandry, undated; 13 folders (Box 40)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes weather, crop, planting, harvesting, hog-killing, fishing, hunting, stock-raising, wood handling signs and useful facts
    - 2:A-2:Y. Omens, Luck-Signs, undated; 23 folders (Box 41)
    - 2:1-2:29. Omens, Luck-Signs, undated; 29 folders (Box 42)
      Includes shooting stars, animals, finding a pin, mirrors, rain, itching body parts, sweeping, singing, sneezing, sleeping, meeting people, whistling
    - 2:30-2:37. Omens, Luck-Signs, undated; 8 folders (Box 43)
      Includes death, devil, marriage, moon, New Year's, tools, clothes, dream omens
    - 3:A-3:B and unclassified. Folk-Medicine, undated; 3 folders (Box 43)
      Includes prenatal influences
    - 3:B:A-3:B-Z. Folk-Medicine, undated; 33 folders (Box 44)
      Includes cures for warts, freckles, rickets, colic, chills, animal bites, indegestion, styes, toothache, pneumonia, mumps, and cuts
    - 3:B:Z(8)-3:B:Z(16). Folk-Medicine, undated; 9 folders (Box 45)
      Includes cures for headaches, earache, consumption, burns, sore throat, asthma, and cramps
    - 4:A-4:C and unclassified. Magic, Charms, undated; 9 folders (Box 45)
      Includes charms to ward off witches, to lift spells
    - 4:D-4:K. Magic, Charms, undated; 6 folders (Box 46)
      Includes charms to make a person love someone, cure disease, break love-tokens, find lost items and for childbirth and death
    - 5:A-5:H. Divination, undated; 7 folders (Box 46)
      Includes dreams, scripture, nature, divining rods, wishes, palms
    - 6:A-6:K. Housewifery, undated; 8 folders (Box 46)
      Includes recipes, raising animals and children and other useful tips
    - 8:A-8:C and unclassified. Pseudoscience, undated; 4 folders (Box 46)
      Includes horsehairs becoming snakes, grass that grows where human blood watered it, cures
    - 9:A-9:E. Folk Expressions, undated; 5 folders (Box 46)
      Includes unusual pronounciations and meanings, peculiar salutations, origins of words, animal calls, figurative expressions
    - 9:F-9:J. Folk Expressions, undated; 4 folders (Box 47)
      Includes idioms, humorous rhymes, unusual names
    - 11:B:1:B-11:B:1:D. Proverbs, Similes, undated; 2 folders (Box 47)
      Includes proverbs, similes, and adages
    - 12. Child Rhymes and Sayings, undated; 1 folders (Box 47)
    - 14:A-14:R. and unclassified. Customs, undated; 12 folders (Box 47)
      Includes holiday, wedding, log-rolling, burial, shooting match, fox-hunting, gander-pulling, cock-fighting, corn-shucking customs
  - Transcripts, Original B, undated; 4
    - 1. Husbandry, undated; 2 folders (Box 48)
    - 2. Omens, Luck-Signs, undated; 4 folders (Box 48)
    - 3. Folk-Medicine, undated; 1 folders (Box 49)
    - 4. Magic, Charms, undated; 1 folders (Box 49)
    - 5. Divination, undated; 1 folders (Box 49)
    - 6. Housewifery, undated; 1 folders (Box 49)
    - 7. Folk-Sermons, undated; 1 folders (Box 49)
    - 8. Pseudoscience, undated; 1 folders (Box 49)
    - 9:A-9:B. Folk-Expressions, undated; 3 folders (Box 50)
      Includes unusual pronounciations
    - 11:A-11:B:1:I Proverbs, Similies, undated; 5 folders (Box 50)
      Includes posies and pithy sayings
    - 12:A-12:R and unclassified. Child Rhymes and Sayings, undated; 19 folders (Box 51)
    - 12:S-12:Z. Child Rhymes and Sayings, undated; 7 folders (Box 52)
    - 13:A-13:D:W. Traditional Games, undated; 8 folders (Box 52)
      Includes toys, dances, and party games
  - Transcripts, Carbon Copy, undated; 5
    - 1. Husbandry, undated; 2 folders (Box 53)
    - 2. Omens, Tokens, Luck-Signs, undated; 4 folders (Box 53)
    - 3:A-3:B. Folk-Medicine, undated; 2 folders (Box 54)
    - 4. Magic, undated; 2 folders (Box 54)
    - 5. Divination, undated; 1 folders (Box 54)
    - 6. Housewifery, undated; 1 folders (Box 54)
    - 7. Folk-Sermons, undated; 1 folders (Box 54)
    - 8. Pseudoscience, undated; 1 folders (Box 54)
    - 9. Folk Expressions, undated; 1 folders (Box 54)
    - 12:A-12:S and unclassified. Child Rhymes and Sayings, undated; 20 folders (Box 55)
    - 12:T-12:Z. Child Rhymes and Sayings, undated; 6 folders (Box 56)
    - 13:A-13:D. Traditional Games, undated; 6 folders (Box 56)
      Includes dances, toys, and songs
    - 14. Customs, undated; 1 folders (Box 56)
    - 15:A-15:Z and unclassified. Legends, Folk-Tales, undated; 22 folders (Box 57)
      Includes tales about plants, ghosts, witches, curses, treasure, fairies, mountains, rivers, valleys
    - 14. Customs, undated; 1 folders (Box 58)
    - 15:A-15:Z and unclassified. Legends, Folk-Tales, undated; 22 folders (Box 58)
    - 16:A:1-16:A:4:D. Folk Songs, undated; 7 folders (Box 58)
      Includes songs about domestic relations, feasts
    - 16:A:4:E-16:B:2. Folk Songs, undated; 25 folders (Box 59)
      Includes songs about domestic relations, outlaw ballads, the sea, humor, Christian legends, work songs
    - 16:B:2:A-16:B:2:D. Folk Songs, undated; 7 folders (Box 60)
      Includes lullabies, nursery songs, party songs, and love songs
    - 16:B:3-16:B:8. Folk Songs, undated; 7 folders (Box 61)
      Includes songs about drinking, gambling, humor, politics, catastrophes, murders and executions
    - 16:B:9-16:12. Folk Songs, undated; 6 folders (Box 62)
      Includes war songs, slave songs, religious songs, African-American folk songs
  - Transcripts, Editor's Work Copies, undated; 6
    - 1:A-1:K and unclassified. Husbandry, undated; 13 folders (Box 63)
    - 2:A-2:C. Omens, Luck-Signs, undated; 4 folders (Box 63)
    - 2:D-2:23. Omens, Luck-Signs, undated; 42 folders (Box 64)
    - 2:24-2:27. Omens, Luck-Signs, undated; 13 folders (Box 65)
    - 3:A-3:B and unclassified. Folk-Medicine, undated; 3 folders (Box 65)
    - 3:B:A-3:B-Z. Folk-Medicine, undated; 42 folders (Box 66)
    - 4:A-4:E. Magic, Charms, undated; 11 folders (Box 67)
    - 4:F-4:L. Magic, Charms, undated; 5 folders (Box 68)
    - 5:A-5:H and unclassified. Divination, undated; 8 folders (Box 68)
    - 6:A-6:K. Housewifery, undated; 8 folders (Box 68)
    - 8:A-8:E and unclassified. Pseudoscience, undated; 4 folders (Box 68)
    - 9:A-9:J. Folk Expressions, undated; 9 folders (Box 68)
    - 11:A. Riddles, undated; 1 folders (Box 69)
    - 11:B-11:D. Proverbs, Similies, undated; 3 folders (Box 69)
    - 12. Child Rhymes and Sayings, undated; 1 folders (Box 69)
    - 14:A-14:R and unclassified. Customs, undated; 12 folders (Box 69)
  - Transcripts, Extra duplicates, Alphabetized, 22 folders (Box 70)
  - Miscellaneous duplicates, 8 folders (Box 71)
  - General Editors' Papers, undated; 1
  - Printed Material and Clippings
    - Songs, Ballads, Reviews of collection (Box 89)
    - Legends, Rhymes, and Miscellaneous related information: sermons, toys, words (Box 89)
    - Beliefs, Customs, Games, Housewifery (Box 89)
- Associate Editors' Papers, 10 boxes
  The Associate Editors' Papers have been organized by editor, with H.M. Belden and A.P. Hudson being grouped together. Belden and Hudson's volumes on songs and ballads include editorial drafts for Volumes 1 and 3, as well as early drafts for Volumes 2 and 3. Paul Brewster's subseries includes returned typescripts for games and rhymes. Wayland D. Hand's subseries includes returned typescripts for superstitions. Claire Leighton's subseries includes typescripts for her to reference in creating woodcut illustrations for the volumes. Jan Schinhan's subseries includes lists of scores and songs. Archer Taylor's subseries includes typescripts and drafts for riddles. Stith Thompson's subseries includes typescripts of tales and legends. Bartlett Jere Whiting's subseries includes typescripts for proverbs. George Wilson's subseries includes typescripts of folk speech.
  - Papers of associate editors Henry Marvin Belden, Arthur Palmer Hudson, Paul Brewster, and Wayland D. Hand (Box 72-77)
  - Papers of associate editor Claire Leighton (Box 77-78)
  - Papers of associate editor Jan Schinhan (Box 78-80)
  - Papers of associate editor Archer Taylor (Box 80)
  - Papers of associate editor Stith Thompson (Box 80-81)
  - Papers of associate editor Bartlett Jere Whiting (Box 81-82)
  - Papers of associate editor George Wilson (Box 82)
- Charles Bond Research Materials, 7 boxes
  The Charles Bond's Research Material Series stems from the work of Charles Bond, a student of Professor Holger O. Nygard of Duke University. Bond opened the collection in 1970-1971, and prepared both an outline as well as a Tabulation of Unpublished Items in the collection. This series also includes correspondence, an index, and card files.
  - "Preliminary Analysis" of the collection (Box 84)
  - "A Tabulation of Unpublished Items" (Box 84)
  - Correspondence with the Library of Congress Archive of Folk Song (Box 84)
  - Study of singing styles in Dark Ridge, North Carolina (Box 84)
  - Abbreviations from headnotes (Box 84)
  - Card files used to prepare "Tabulation" (Box 85-88)
  - Seven 8-inch reels of magnetic tape of unpublished songs (Preservation Masters) (Box 146)
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Digital listening copies are available.]
  - Seven 8-inch reels of magnetic tape of unpublished songs (Reproduction Masters) (Box 147)
  - Digital use copies of Reproduction Masters (Box 147)
  - Indexes to tapes of unpublished recordings, alphabetical by title and alphabetical by artist, 1971; 2 folders (Box 147)